Clore PTS structure paper
* All the protein– protein interfaces are characterized by large buried acces-sible surface areas ranging from 1200 to 1800 A °2, with approximately equal contributions from both partners. 
* The interaction surfaces for HPr and Enzymes IIB are convex, whereas those of EIN and Enzymes IIA are concave, providing shape complementarity. 
* The active site residue is offset from the center of the binding site. Surface complementarity is largely provided by the hydrophobic residues, whereas electrostatic interactions serve to modulate affinity and direct the exact relative orientation of the partner proteins within a given complex. Sequences comparisons over several species indicate that although the absolute identity of the hydrophobic residues at the interface may vary, the network of intermolecular hydrophobic interactions is preserved and substitutions are in general compensatory, such that the packing density at the interface across different species remains largely unperturbed 
* HPr uses essentially the same convex surface to interact with all its partners, and all charged residues on the interaction surface of HPr are positive (Figure 2A, top row). A key feature of the interactions of HPr with its partner proteins is redundancy of charged residues, such that the disposition of the complementary negatively charged residues on the partner proteins need not be identical. Thus, not all charged residues present at the protein–protein interface are involved in salt bridge inter-actions. 
* Another key feature of the binding surfaces that permits specific recognition of a wide variety of partners is side chain conformational plasticity, illustrated in Figure 3A for several side chain interactions between HPr and EIN or IIAGlc [47]. For example, the side chain of Phe48 undergoes a conformational switch from one rotamer in the EIN–HPr complex to another in the IIAGlc–HPr complexes, thereby permitting Phe48 to interact with hydrophobic compo-nents on the partner proteins, specifically the methyl groups of Leu79, Leu85 and Ile108 for EIN, and the backbone residues of a b-sheet for IIAGlc (Figure 3A, left panel). Likewise, Arg17 of HPr interacts in one side con-formation with Glu67 and Glu68 of EIN and in another conformation with Asp38 and Asp94 of IIAGlc (Figure 3A, right panel) 
* The phoshoryl transition states are shown in the lower rows of Figure 2A,B. The phosphoryl group and the active site histidines and/or cysteines lie on a bed of hydrophobic residues, and the phosphoryl group itself is stabilized by hydrogen bonding interactions involving polar (Thr, Ser, and His) or charged (Arg) residues. 